Finding Aid for Edward W. Mill papers, 1930-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward W. Mill papers 1930-1977
Mill, Edward W. (Edward William), 1916-1977.
1 microfilm roll
9 linear feet
85312 Aa 2
Teaching fellow in political science at the University of Michigan, later foreign service officer with the Division of Philippine Affairs in the Office of Far Eastern Affairs, U. S. Department of State, and professor of diplomacy and world affairs at Occidental College. Academic files, correspondence, papers relating to his work and interest in the Philippine Islands and Indonesia, topical files concerning his various academic interests, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
In 1978, Mill’s sister, Dorothy Mill Walls (donor no. 6202 ) allowed the library to microfilm Philippine-related materials which she had promised to the archives of the Dept. of Foreign Affairs, Republic of the Philippines. In 1981, the library received Mill’s papers that had been stored in the library of Occidental College. Additional papers were received in 1986.
The collection is open to research.
Edward William Mill was born in Mason City, Illinois on June 14, 1916. He received a B.A. from the University of Wisconsin (1940) and an M.A. in political science from the University of Michigan (1941).
From December 1943 to April 1945, Mill was in charge of Philippine work at the Office of Strategic Services. In April 1945 he was transferred to the Division of Philippine affairs, Office of Far Eastern Affairs of the Department of State. As Assistant Chief of the Division of Philippine affairs, Mill played a major role in implementing the grant of independence to the Republic of the Philippines on July 4, 1946. He drafted the Proclamation of Philippine Independence by which President Truman proclaimed the independence of the Philippines. He also drafted the first treaty between the two countries, the Treaty of General Relations.
Mill served as Director of the Philippine Foreign Affairs Training Program of the U.S. Department of State from 1945-1948 under which the career foreign service of the Republic of the Philippines was developed. Mill was engaged in the actual training of Philippine diplomats and assisted in the establishment of the new Philippine Department of Foreign affairs.
In 1948, Mill was assigned to the U.S. Embassy in Manila where his major task was to organize and develop a new Political Section for the U.S. Embassy. In a second assignment as a Foreign Service Reserve officer, Mill was assigned to Indonesia in 1949 to re-establish and build a new American Consulate at Surabaya, East Java.
Resuming his academic career in 1952, Mill completed his doctoral studies at Princeton in 1954. In 1955, he served as Chairman of the Political Science Department and assistant to the President at Rockford College (Illinois). In 1959, he was employed by Long Island University to organize a new Political Science Department. During the next three years, he developed new undergraduate and graduate programs in political science and international relations at Long Island University.
In 1962, Mill was appointed to the Stuart Chevalier Chair in Diplomacy and World Affairs at Occidental College (California). As Chairman of the Chevalier Program in Diplomacy and World Affairs, Mill was primarily concerned with the education of outstanding young people for international service.
Mill received, in 1964, the highest award made by the Republic of the Philippines, the Order of Sikatuna.
Edward Mill died on July 13, 1977.
The Edward Mill Collection is divided into seven series: Personal; Academic Papers; Correspondence; Far Eastern Materials; Topical File (largely correspondence); Visual Materials; and Microfilmed materials.
Subjects:
Diplomats.; Indonesia.; Mill, Edward W. (Edward William), 1916-1977.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; United States. Dept. of State.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Beauty shops.; Indonesia.; Interiors.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Travel.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series is composed of biographical material, including a diary from Mill's student years at the University of Michigan.
  - Biographical Materials (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Mill Family in England (Box 1)
  - Birthday Celebrations (Box 1)
  - Diary (Box 1)
- Academic Papers
  Academic Papers includes student papers, addresses, book reviews, bibliographies, and copies of articles. There is also a typescript of Mill's book The Conduct of Philippine Foreign Relations.
  - Addresses (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1)
  - Typescripts (Box 1)
  - Articles (Box 1)
  - Student Papers 1935-1940 (Box 1)
  - "The Conduct of Philippine Foreign Relations" (Ph.D. dissertation) 1954 (Box 2)
  - The Conduct of Philippine Foreign Relations (typescript of book) (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series consists of two subseries. The first subseries contains mainly incoming correspondence from the late 1930's to the 1970's, while the second subseries contains out-going correspondence from the 1940's to the early 1950's.
  - In-Coming (mainly)
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1930-1946, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - 1947-1978, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Out-Going
    - 1940-1953, 5 folders (Box 3)
- Far Eastern Materials
  The Far Eastern materials series includes a subseries of correspondence which documents Mill's work in the Philippines and Indonesia. There is also considerable material dealing with the Philippines Foreign Affairs Training Program.
  - Correspondence undated, 1943-1969, 11 folders (Box 4)
  - Topical File
    - Asian Trips 1963, 1967, 1969, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Indonesia
      - General (Box 4)
      - Task Force 1972 (Box 4)
    - Philippines
      - Bureau of the Budget (Box 4)
      - Department of Foreign Affairs (Box 4)
      - Interviews with Philippine Leaders (Box 4)
      - Office of Foreign Relations (Box 4)
      - Philippine Foreign Affairs Training Program (Box 4)
      - Reorganization of the Government (Box 4)
      - Reports
        - Jingco, Betty. "Committees on Foreign Affairs of the Congress of the Philippines," circa 1954 (Box 4)
        - Millegan, Lloyd. "Progress Report," July 16-September 30, 1956 (Box 4)
        - Vite, Doroteo, "My Country and I" (M.A. 1943) (Box 4)
      - Republic Act of 708 (Box 5)
      - Romulo, Carlos P. (Box 5)
    - South East Asia Task Force (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Topical File
  The Topical File series includes material on Mill's students, friends, relatives, and fellow faculty members. The series, which is largely correspondence, also contains material on the various academic institutions that Edward Mill served.
  - Cosmos Club (Box 5)
  - Honolulus Municipal Government Charter Commission (Box 5)
  - Individuals
    - Alba, Marilon (Box 5)
    - Beauchamp, William (Box 5)
    - Bell, Marie (Box 5)
    - Bonafous, Marie (Box 5)
    - Bullis, Harry (Box 5)
    - Chen, Rolet (Box 5)
    - Cudd Brown, J. (Box 5)
    - Douglas, Paul (Box 5)
    - Dvinell, Emerson (Box 5)
    - Ebenstein, William (Box 5)
    - Forsen, Jan (Box 5)
    - Foss, Bert (Box 5)
    - Francis, Tom (Box 5)
    - Kuan, Edward (Box 5)
    - Lai, W.H. (Box 5)
    - Leggett, Robert (Box 5)
    - Lockett, Thomas (Box 5)
    - Markham, William (Box 5)
    - McClory, Robert (Box 5)
    - McGee, Gale (Box 5)
    - McKelvey, Raymond (Box 5)
    - Meinheit, Joe (Box 5)
    - Meinheit, Marjorie and Susie (Box 5)
    - Millegan, Lloyd (Box 5)
    - Mitchell, Mike (Box 5)
    - Moore, Curt (Box 5)
    - Morris, David (Box 5)
    - Myers, Ron (Box 5)
    - Nevins, Allan (Box 5)
    - Novogrod, R.J. (Box 5)
    - Novotney, Jan (Box 5)
    - Pakkasem, Phit (Box 5)
    - Paul, Jim (Box 5)
    - Peng, Minz-min (Box 5)
    - Pernacciaro, Samuel (Box 5)
    - Puribhat, Arakitti (Box 5)
    - Reath, Richard (Box 5)
    - Record, Jeff (Box 5)
    - Remencius, Len (Box 5)
    - Reuther, David (Box 5)
    - Riggins, Bill (Box 5)
    - Rothback, Lou (Box 5)
    - Rolle, A.F. (Box 5)
    - Rugani, Frank (Box 5)
    - Salter, Jack (Box 5)
    - Schefer, E. Edward (Box 5)
    - Schott, Ilse (Box 5)
    - Shaw, Mike (Box 5)
    - Shaw, Peter (Box 5)
    - Solarz, Andy (Box 6)
    - Spence, Floyd (Box 6)
    - Spika, Dan (Box 6)
    - Sprout, Harold (Box 6)
    - Stanton, Joyce (Box 6)
    - Steinegger, Egon (Box 6)
    - Sulit, Perla (Box 6)
    - Sun, Ho Sheng (Box 6)
    - Tamano, Mamintal (Box 6)
    - Taylor, Earle (Box 6)
    - Tepper, Marvin (Box 6)
    - Troxel, Oliver (Box 6)
    - Vanicelli, Primo (Box 6)
    - Walcott, Chuck (Box 6)
    - Weisberg, Harvey (Box 6)
    - Weller, Col. R.C. (Box 6)
    - Wells, Bert (Box 6)
    - Wilbur, Sharon (Box 6)
    - Williams, Bill (Box 6)
    - Winkelhake, Claude (Box 6)
    - Withrow, Roger (Box 6)
    - Wollner, Mary (Box 6)
    - Wood, Frances (Box 6)
    - Yee, Lockett and Eddie (Box 6)
    - Yee, Ting (Box 6)
    - Young, Arthur (Box 6)
  - Long Island University (Box 6)
  - Los Angles Times (Box 6)
  - Michigan Historical Collections (Box 6)
  - Occidental College
    - General (Box 6)
    - Chevalier Program (Box 6)
    - Student Letters (Box 6)
  - Rockford College (Box 6)
  - United States-Japan Symposium 1975 (Box 6)
  - University of Hawaii (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    (Note: These boxes have not been processed)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    (continued)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes photographs and albums documents Mill's work in the Philippines and Indonesia.
  - Photographs
    - California, Occidental College (Box 9)
    - California, Occidental College, students (Box 9)
    - China (Box 9)
    - Colleagues (Box 9)
    - Conferences
      - Model UN Security Council 1960 (Box 9)
      - Rockford, Ill. and Los Angeles (Box 9)
    - Family and friends, 2 envelopes (Box 9)
    - Flag Day (birthday) parties (Box 9)
    - Groups, unidentified (Box 9)
    - Indonesia
      - Surabaja (Box 9)
      - Other areas (Box 9)
    - Japan and Korea (Box 9)
    - Japan-U.S. Economic Relations Symposium, Occidental College 1975 (Box 9)
    - Leggett, Robert L., California congressman (Box 9)
    - Long Island University, Brooklyn, N.Y. (Box 9)
    - Philippine Foreign Affairs Training Program, Washington, D.C. 1945 (Box 9)
    - Philippines
      - 1940s (Box 9)
      - 1960s (Box 9)
    - Portraits and snapshots (Box 9)
    - Time-Life group 1965 (Box 9)
    - Travel
      - Africa and Asia (Box 9)
      - Bali 1951 (Box 9)
      - England 1971 (Box 9)
      - Europe 1971-1972 (Box 9)
      - Turkey (Box 9)
      - Thailand and Singapore (Box 9)
      - U.S., Illinois and Iowa (Box 9)
      - U.S., Wisconsin and western trip (Box 9)
      - U.S., San Francisco (Box 9)
      - U.S., Texas, Arizona, and Wyoming (Box 9)
      - U.S., Washington, D.C. (Box 9)
    - Washington, D.C. 1940s (Box 9)
    - Youth-Wisconsin scenes (Box 9)
  - Albums
    - Small tan album: Djombang, Indonesia 1950 (Box 9)
      (includes scenes of war damage)
    - Black and brown album: Malang, Indonesia 1950 (Box 9)
      (includes Mill visit to textile factory)
    - Large blue-green album: Indonesia 1950-1951 (Box 9)
      (includes Mill with staff, social events, and friends)
    - Green album with border: Family photographs (Box 9)
- Microfilmed records, 1 roll of microfilm, Micro AA
  The Microfilm Material series consists of correspondence and other documents that Mill had wanted to be deposited in the archives of the department of foreign affairs of the Republic of the Philippines.
  - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
    - Pablo A. Pena 1946 (Reel 1)
    - Generoso Provido 1947 (Reel 1)
    - Aurelia Ramos 1946-1947 (Reel 1)
    - Narciso Ramos 1951-1954 (Reel 1)
    - Carlos P. Romulo 1947-1955 (Reel 1)
    - Eduardo L. Rosal 1947 (Reel 1)
    - Simon (?) Roxas 1948 (Reel 1)
    - R.H. Severino 1947 (Reel 1)
    - Vincente I. Singian 1946-1947 (Reel 1)
    - Tagakotto Sotto 1947-1948 (Reel 1)
    - Eutiquio O. Sta. Romana 1946-1947 (Reel 1)
    - Benjamin T. Tirona 1947 (Reel 1)
    - Roman V. Ubaldo 1947-1948 (Reel 1)
    - Vincente Villamin 1946-1948 (Reel 1)
    - Alejandro D. Yango 1947 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence with Foreign Service Training Program Trainees 1947-1956 (Reel 1)
  - Chronological file 1943-1948 (Reel 1)
  - Chronological file 1948-1957 (Reel 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Reel 1)